JAVAD BAYAZI

Montreal, Quebec, Canada

③Google Scholar: scholar.google.com/citations → GitHub: github.com/MohammadJavadD

𝚱Website: mohammadjavadd.github.io/home

Profile

Driven by curiosity and an analytical mindset, I bring a fresh perspective to any Machine Learning team. My experience spans research, teaching, and leading teams in AI-focused projects. I'm experienced in developing deep learning models and excel at managing multiple responsibilities, from academia to industry.

Technical Skills

Programming languages: Python, C, Matlab, R, Bash, SQL

Developer Tools: Git, PyTest, Docker, VS Code, Jupyter Notebook, Unix shell,

Data Mining and Machine Learning:PyTorch, TensorFlow, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn

Technologies/Frameworks: Wandb, HuggingFace, Hydra, Slurm, Cluster, HPC

Cloud: Google Cloud Platform, Amazon Web Services (AWS SageMaker)

Domain: Computer Vision (CV), Natural Language Processing (NLP), Generative AI, Large Language Models (LLMs),

Large Multimodal Models (LMMs), Foundation Models, Time Series

Work Experience

Mila - Quebec Artificial Intelligence Institute

Jan. 2019 - Present

Graduate Research Assistant - PhD Student

Montreal, Canada

- Designed and deployed large-scale foundation models for time series analysis. These models inherently possess general capabilities, requiring no further tuning for immediate application in finance, medicine, weather, and traffic.
- Developed strategies and benchmarks to enhance the robustness and reliability of deep learning models in time series analysis, effectively addressing real-world challenges to ensure safe and reliable machine learning deployment.
- Published 3+ peer-reviewed articles in highly ranked journals, 5+ papers in top-tier conferences, and preprints, which have been widely utilized in subsequent research and projects.
- Collaborated and communicated effectively with multidisciplinary teams (CAE, NRC, Marinvent and Morgan Stanley) to translate research findings into actionable and scalable solutions for several industries.

NBML - National Brain Mapping Laboratory

2017 – **2018** *Tehran, Iran*

Data Scientist

- Analyzed signals and images using computational tools to facilitate clinical decision-making.
- Performed statistical analysis on diverse datasets to identify trends and patterns in time series
- Developed pipelines for researchers, medical doctors, and practitioners to study brain function and therapeutic methods.

Hummingbird - AI startup

July, 2022 - July, 2023

Chief Executive Officer

Montréal, Canada

• Leading development of foundation models for time series analysis, enabling more accurate planning and decision-making in finance, economics, governance, and medicine.

Education

University of Montreal (UMontréal - Mila (Quebec Artificial Intelligence Institute))

2019 - Present Montreal, Canada

Doctor of Philosophy in Biomedical Engineering (Machine Learning)

- Topic: R3: Robust and Reliable Deep Learning Models for Real-World Applications
- Supervisors: Jocelyn Faubert (UdeM, FaubertLab), <u>Irina Rish</u> (UdeM, Mila)

Shahed University

2014 - 2018

Master of Science in Biomedical Engineering - Bioelectrics

Tehran, Iran

• Topic: Causality and Information Flow in Multivariate Time Series

Yazd University

2010 - 2014

Yazd. Iran

Bachelor of Science in Electrical Engineering

• Topic: Smart Greenhouse Monitoring and Control System Using Industrial Microprocessors

Coursework and Certificate

Coursework and Certificate		
• Deep Representation Learning	• Artificial Neural Network	• Biomedical Systems Modeling
• Generative AI with LLMs	• Digital Signal and Image Processing	• Microcontrollers
• Statistical Pattern Recognition	• Nonlinear Dynamics and Chaos	• SQL for Data Science
Interests		
 Artificial Intelligence (AI) Machine Learning (ML) Deep Learning (DL) Representation Learning (RL) 	 Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) Out of Distribution Generalization Foundation Models (FM) Transfer Learning (TL) 	 AI for Medicine (AI4M) AI for Finance (AI4M) Time Series Analysis (TS) Large language model (LLM)
Colooted Dublications		

Selected Publications

- Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., ..., Faubert, J., & Rish, I. (2023). Amplifying Pathological Detection in EEG Signaling Pathways through ... Transfer Learning. CIBM, [Link, IF:7.7, Acceptance Rate:13%][DL,TL,AI4M]
- Rasul, K., Ashok, A., ..., Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., ..., & Rish, I. (2024). Lag-Llama: Towards Foundation Models for Probabilistic Time Series Forecasting. [Link][DL,TL,LLM,TS]
- Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., ..., & Rish, I. (2023). Introducing Brain Foundation Models. [DL,TL,LLM, TS, AI4M]
- Darvishi Bayazi, M. J., Law, A., Romero, S. M., Jennings, S., Rish, I., & Faubert, J. (2023) Beyond performance: The role of task demand, effort, and individual differences. Scientific Reports. [Link, IF:4.9] [ML,TS, AI4M]
- Gagnon-Audet, J. C., Ahuja, K., Darvishi-Bayazi, M. J., Dumas, G., & Rish, I. (2023) WOODS: Benchmarks for Out-of-Distribution Generalization in Time Series Tasks. TMLR, ICLR 2024. [Link, Featured][DL,TL,TS]
- Albuquerque I, Monteiro J, Darvishi M, Falk TH, & Mitliagkas I. (2019) Generalizing to unseen domains via distribution matching. arXiv preprint arXiv:1911.00804. [Link][DL,TL,TS]
- Ghaffari, H., Yoonessi, A., Darvishi, M. J., & Ahmadi, A. (2018). Normal electrical activity of the brain in obsessive-compulsive patients after anodal stimulation of the left dorsolateral prefrontal cortex. Basic and clinical neuroscience, 9(2), 135. [Link][TS, AI4M]

Teaching Activity

UdeM/Mila Jan. 2022 - May 2022

Teaching Assistant at IFT 6135 - Representation Learning - SSL, NLP, CV

Montreal, Canada

- Assisted Dr. Aaron Courville, a pioneer in AI and deep learning, in teaching self-supervised learning techniques.
- Provided support to students by addressing questions and assisting with coding issues during the course.

Ivado/Mila Mar. 2021 – Apr. 2021

Teaching Assistant at Deep Learning Spring School

Montreal, Canada

 Assisted machine learning practitioners from various industries in understanding and implementing advanced deep learning techniques.

Honors & Awards

Artificial Intelligence Applications in Healthcare	2021
Microsoft Diversity Award	2020
Bourse d'exemption des droits de scolarité supplémentaires	2019 - 2020
Master's Thesis Research Grants from Cognitive Science and Technologies Council	2018
Distinguished Student, Ranked 1^{th} among all graduated students of Biomedical Engineering department	2018
Ministry of Science and Technology scholarship (7 years, BSc, MSc)	2010 - 2017

Leadership / Extracurricular

SIGHT Montreal Sep. 2019 – Jan. 2024

President, Vice-president, and Webmaster

IEEE

NBML

- Organized AI4Good event and the AI against COVID-19 competition, raised 20K⁺ CAD from Microsoft Canada
- Designed and launched the website of the group

 1^{st} and 2^{nd} IBCIC Jan. 2017 – 2018

Vice-Chair of the Executive Committee

• Designed a Brain-computer Interface competition, TV Report

Languages

English: Proficient | Persian: Native | French: Intermediate (actively learning)